[SPEAKER_02]: Does anybody have any ideas how to start the discussion about the right suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: The wrong suffering is craving to get rid of suffering by acting out of
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, eh... let's approach it from a different angle.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it eh... Is it the case that you start the practice so as to get rid of suffering as quickly as possible?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is that the motivation behind starting the practice?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that would be quite often the case, taking on the practice so that I can get rid of suffering today, if I can.
[SPEAKER_02]: But is there anything wrong with that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's the question.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like the Buddha teaches only one thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: He has said dukkha and the ending of dukkha.
[SPEAKER_04]: So if someone is listening with the intention of freeing themselves from suffering, then what's the issue with that?
[SPEAKER_03]: The thing is that it's already what we are doing by looking for sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_03]: We look for a way out of suffering as quick as possible so we engage in any other distraction or any like...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, do you see what dukkha is when you start out the practice?
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's what I was going to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, if you're you're kind of going into it with the, like, I need to end suffering, like, as fast as possible, like, what you're trying to end might not actually be what the Buddha is teaching the end of.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you could basically say there are symptoms of the illness and then there's the actual illness.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, you can engage in various strategies to get rid of the symptoms of the illness.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, ironically, the symptoms of the illness are... you need to experience them in order to diagnose properly what the sickness is.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you try to get rid of the symptoms as quickly as possible,
[SPEAKER_02]: You won't be able to actually understand suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you could even say the practice doesn't start with trying to get rid of suffering as quickly as possible.
[SPEAKER_02]: It starts to... starts with learning how to... to put it in a certain way, how to suffer properly.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that doesn't mean, like, seeking out the suffering in the sense of self-mortification, neither bodily self-mortification nor mental self-mortification.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just that...
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not creating that suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's more like that suffering is already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just that we are so trained in avoiding it, circumventing it through various ways, that we live as if it's not there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, learning how to suffer doesn't mean making yourself suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: It just means recognizing the suffering that is already there when you stop
[SPEAKER_02]: Chasing, as you said, sensuality, acting out of unwholesome states and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when you stop that, the first symptom that's going to reveal itself is that the tendency where, you know, you've been inclining the mind in that direction and now it wants to keep going there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, that discrepancy is going to be felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why, practically speaking, taking on the practice on the right level means
[SPEAKER_02]: At least, initially, some degree of suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, eh... basically, you...
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't... if you just... you can be sure that if you started your practice and then, at no point in time, you had to experience any kind of, at least mental, uneasiness, there's a very high... at least today, you know, from the starting point that most of us come from... You would be doing it wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, there's a very high chance that your practice is just going with the grain of the same
[SPEAKER_02]: As you said just now, like tendencies of sensuality, but just in a more subtle level.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why the Buddha said there are four types of practice, like painful practice with quick results, painful practice with slow results, pleasant practice with quick results, and pleasant practice with slow results.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then,
[SPEAKER_02]: It depends... the pleasantness of the practice depends on what is the intensity of the desire, aversion, and delusion that you start with.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how the suttas define it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, most of us, virtually all of us today, start with intense quantities of lust, aversion, and delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why people hear about renunciation, and even in idea, like in abstraction,
[SPEAKER_02]: Not even in, you know, in having to get themselves to actually do it, but just thinking about it, is already unbearable for most people.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's a testament to how much pollution we start with, and accordingly then, it's just... it's just the sickness is more serious, is more grave,
[SPEAKER_02]: So, as a result of that, the symptoms that you have to put up with, while solving that sickness, are most likely going to be more unpleasant than not.
[SPEAKER_02]: So...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like a... like a cancer patient.
[SPEAKER_02]: If he... if he's basically trying to find the quickest way to not feel displeasure on account of the cancer, there are various kinds of mental gymnastics that you can go... that you can achieve that goal with.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you can basically...
[SPEAKER_02]: Forget about it in various ways.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can distract yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can practice, you know, psychologization, rationalization techniques to not acknowledge the fact that you have cancer.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that is factually going to result in not suffering right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: But are you actually fixing the illness?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, going through the chemotherapy, to put it that way, has unpleasant effects.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, if you go through it, like, it's just going to be... none of the suffering that you're going to go through as a result of that chemotherapy can be compared with the suffering of dying, on account of, you know, prioritizing your present
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so a certain longer-term perspective is necessary.
[SPEAKER_04]: In a certain sense, I'm inclined to say that it is better to even emphasize the future, what is going to happen, than the present.
[SPEAKER_04]: There can be something quite inauthentic in saying
[SPEAKER_04]: I just have to be present here and now.
[SPEAKER_04]: All there is, is this.
[SPEAKER_04]: This present moment.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is what my meditation is about, because that can be an easy avenue to deny that this body is basically going downhill, even if right now you are still healthy.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the Buddha himself reflected, while young, I'm subject to old age.
[SPEAKER_04]: When healthy, I'm subject to sickness.
[SPEAKER_04]: While alive, I'm subject to death.
[SPEAKER_04]: How else can you be subjected to death?
[SPEAKER_04]: So that is what is waiting.
[SPEAKER_04]: But there is a way out of that, but not by ignoring
[SPEAKER_04]: That's future direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so that's... you brought it up, like, the perfect example of these ways to get rid of the suffering as quickly as possible is this, like, virtually most practices today, the direction that they revolve around is this present moment observation.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's essentially taking you, like, you know, cancer patient focusing on all my knees, how I feel right now, and the sensations in my back and stuff.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if he were to gain any perspective, he would see that that's not actually worth it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not a good deal.
[SPEAKER_02]: The thing is, like, obviously the analogy sounds quite dumb, like nobody would actually do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the thing is, when it comes to the suffering of craving, you don't recognize yourself being sick in the first place.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why the analogy doesn't apply fully.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you were to see clearly the predicament that you're in, you would be incapable of falling into that kind of ignorance of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You would... As the Buddha said, there's only two
[SPEAKER_02]: There are two possible results of recognizing the suffering that you're subject to.
[SPEAKER_02]: One of them is basically falling into vexation, like lamentation and...
[SPEAKER_02]: Madness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Madness, you could say, or noble search, which is, I need to solve this problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no other thing that can come in the way of that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, there's nothing more important than that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, whatever other problems you thought you have up until that time, suddenly are no longer your problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, that is because you now have inherited one bigger problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Namely, your existence in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you say that another shortcoming of the analogy is... so, like, when you talk about chemotherapy having kind of negative effects, that's like stuff that you wouldn't have otherwise, like your hair falling out.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, that's kind of the one that comes to mind, whereas with trying to align yourself with the right view,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're actually... it's not creating any new suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just kind of highlighting what's already there that you've been facing away from.
[SPEAKER_02]: Eventually, you will get to recognize that that suffering was already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the ignorant mind might very well start with the wrong idea that, no, this is being created by this restraint that I'm doing now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why you might fall into the view that, if I just don't do this practice, I could genuinely be happy.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is...
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not really the case.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, it's a relative, sort of, it's like, again, the happiness of... ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, ignorance is bliss, as that saying goes, but it's not actually... Yeah, it says that.
[SPEAKER_04]: There is the happiness that is ignoble, and there is the happiness that is noble.
[SPEAKER_04]: And of these two, obviously, the noble happiness is the foremost one.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, practically speaking, you can't be... you basically have to relinquish the idea of what you think happiness is.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to revise that idea, let's say.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to recognize that anything that you could get
[SPEAKER_02]: Unless you have already gone through a significant amount of the gradual training, renunciation, and authenticity, and some potentially tumultuous, you know, developments, the idea
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what's the difference between a happy mind and a mind that is... and a happiness that is based on knowing the mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I wanted to dedicate the next talk to that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right happiness, right suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, right suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: The thing you could say, though, is that that suffering, then, is like...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not that you take it on for some indeterminate period of time and then you get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even later, it's not... it's... you actually free yourself from it by understanding it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you never find like a kind of a...
[SPEAKER_02]: Some sort of magical place where you hide.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's really... You have to go through it, in a sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the lack of understanding that makes that suffering a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, lack of understanding makes unpleasant feeling of any kind
[SPEAKER_02]: It makes it, turns it into dukkha, turns it into suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's that, sort of, the two arrows.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't say that it's, you know, it's... a person is hit by the second arrow because they haven't found some magical, sort of, state that protects them from the suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: It says, on account of them not knowing the nature of those feelings, that is why they are hit by suffering when unpleasant feeling arises.
[SPEAKER_04]: And also, when unpleasant feeling arises for them, they don't have craving for it, and they basically crave against the unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, well, when unpleasant feeling arises, the only way that they know how to deal with it is by getting pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, you can be sure then that any... well, that's a good point.
[SPEAKER_02]: Any pleasure that comes kind of in place of the suffering, to replace it,
[SPEAKER_02]: That is sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if it's not the pleasure of specific coarse sights, sounds, smells, tastes and touches.
[SPEAKER_02]: The pleasure of, let's say, a concentration practice that people will be doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: The fact that it comes in place of the suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: It kind of steals the space from it so that it can't be there.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is the principle of sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like covering it up.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so when that's understood, when desire for sensual pleasure is seen as basically the only way the ordinary person knows to deal with his suffering, i.e.
[SPEAKER_04]: he's not dealing with it on the right level, then, by not engaging with that,
[SPEAKER_04]: And by not covering it up with the methods and techniques you were just explaining as well, what comes into sight is that underlying suffering which was there the whole time already.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so that's the point.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's important when you do that, when you start coming into contact with or familiarizing yourself with that liability to suffering that was already there, that you don't develop a view that
[SPEAKER_02]: It's because of the practice that this is happening.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's because of your resistance, really, to that unpleasant feeling that has revealed itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's painful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not because, in and of itself, like, this restraint is always going to be, you know, this, this, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: In fact, that's why, that's many of the times, that's why people develop a kind of view of nibbāna being a almost mystical, magical state, because that's the only thing that can compensate for, again, replacing the pleasure of... the pain that you might have taken through renunciation.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need something else now to, kind of, down the line, come
[SPEAKER_02]: It plays with it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, and it also covers over that it is because of one's own actions, acting out of greed, hatred and illusion, that nibbāna isn't realized.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you also realize that that suffering is there, not because of some cosmic condition that is not going in your favor.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's there, like you're responsible for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why that... and at the same time, that is the
[SPEAKER_02]: The positive, let's say, aspect of it is that it might seem very bleak, like, oh, suffering, suffering, but the good news is you are entirely responsible for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the beginning, you don't understand why it's happening.
[SPEAKER_02]: It feels like it's coming by itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you understand that that suffering is entirely because of your mental attitude.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is why it can end as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: The mental attitude that you don't yet see, but you will never get to see it if you don't withdraw yourself from the things that, again, from these immediate solutions.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so in the beginning, if someone is understanding this rightly, and they go about it rightly, experientially, it might look like their suffering increases.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: But this needs to be understood as not necessarily a bad thing, if it's against the right understanding.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the...
[SPEAKER_02]: The rule of thumb there would be, you make sure that if your mental displeasure is increasing, that it's not because you're actively seeking it out and trying to torture yourself, but because you are, like, you're simply refraining
[SPEAKER_02]: from covering it up.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're simply just seeing what was already there on account of you not doing certain things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not that you're trying to, you know, get yourself wound up on purpose or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so, what commonly happens, if this is not understood,
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, someone might have been practicing in lay life, for example, certain meditation methods, techniques, concentration practices, they become inspired, want to become a monk, take on the Patimokkha training rules, 227 training rules, that from the day that you are a bhikkhu, you have to keep them, and for quite a few months or years, whatever they thought their practice was,
[SPEAKER_04]: Is this going to be a big mess?
[SPEAKER_04]: Because they have a lot of doubts.
[SPEAKER_04]: Did I break this precept?
[SPEAKER_04]: Did I do that properly?
[SPEAKER_04]: And so, on account of actually learning how to operate within the patimokha training rules, which is the first thing that you should do as a monk, that's going to reveal the mental displeasure of having doubts and when I'm holding these precepts rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so, they might think, well, my meditation is going down the drain, but actually, what they thought was meditation, was actually never really meditation.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, they are making progress, because now, they are in a position to actually recognize
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you see, if something as simple as just not being able to keep some rules can can arouse that suffering, means you were already liable to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if you have never ordained and stayed in your perfect controlled lay environment, where nobody's telling you what to do, the fact that this ended up happening means
[SPEAKER_02]: You didn't actually address those defilements.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, this is, at best, exposing them.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not that they were not there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you want to be... that's the common thread, where you want to be exposing these liabilities.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the... you want to be, as we discussed in the talk on authenticity, the problem is that the natural
[SPEAKER_02]: The way of living is like, how do I recognize these liabilities the least?
[SPEAKER_02]: How can I go about that?
[SPEAKER_02]: But, you actually have to go against the grain.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the attitude that goes with the development of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Going against the grain means that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Instead of habitually covering up these liabilities, you recognize, actually, the only way that I can protect myself from something,
[SPEAKER_02]: Rightly is if I know that it's there.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the only way.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or that it's coming.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or that it could come.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: If, like, you can, you know, there's going to be an earthquake and you just... well, the same thing, like cancer, earthquake, whatever, any sort of thing that might arouse fear or displeasure in your mind, you can either
[SPEAKER_02]: prioritize right now feeling good and ignoring that it could happen or you could see that that liability as a chance to develop yourself even before it comes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the whole thing with sickness, aging, and death.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not that you kind of find something that... some special strategy that will protect you when those things come.
[SPEAKER_02]: You actually develop yourself right now by recognizing that displeasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, when those things come, you won't be moved by that displeasure.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so, what is then the right development for someone who recognizes that old age sickness, death, is coming their way?
[SPEAKER_04]: That they are liable to it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Not that it could happen, but that it is going to happen.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just a question of time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, and and as that sutta said, there is... the Buddha told that king, imagine that there's four great mountains approaching you.
[SPEAKER_02]: One from the north, one from the south, one from the east, and one from the west.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you have no way to run.
[SPEAKER_02]: And basically, that's birth, sickness, aging, and death.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, that is the sort of recognition that can
[SPEAKER_02]: Just having that recognition is already quite... being able to keep that context in your mind is already a significant progress from the starting point of the average person.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, once you start recognizing that, you also need to see that
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, unless you have developed virtue, sensory strains, and all these prerequisites beforehand, going too far into it, reflecting on it, pondering on it, too much, might probably result in, you know, quite unpleasant consequences, because you are not, like, the only... when you haven't had at least some taste of the
[SPEAKER_02]: ease of giving things up, of actual renunciation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't know anything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, it's like this thing is crushing you, and the only satisfaction that you know is outside of those mountains that are crushing you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, practically speaking, you won't be able to keep your sanity, and contemplate sickness, aging, and death fully, properly, and accurately, unless you have developed that criteria of virtue.
[SPEAKER_02]: Either you will not be seeing it
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if somebody's gonna think... You see, having been...
[SPEAKER_04]: If somebody's going to realize, having been born, I am at once old enough to die, so it's not birth and then death and then my life sort of in in the in the middle.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: Being here means right now I am liable to old age, sickness, death.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the immediacy of birth, old age, sickness, death.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, what is the point of of building up anything
[SPEAKER_04]: And making myself more dependent on acquisitions, on things in the world, if at any moment beyond my control, that can be taken away from me.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, rather than learning how to be with the breath for 30 seconds rather than 20, or for a few minutes rather than one, people would be coming closer to what the Buddha was teaching by asking themselves
[SPEAKER_04]: What am I practically doing in my life?
[SPEAKER_04]: And am I building up attachments and acquisitions?
[SPEAKER_04]: Which means that when they are going to be taken away from me, it's going to be more painful.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I know right now, if I'm honest and quiet and on my own, that anxiety in the back of my mind, like, oh,
[SPEAKER_04]: Stuff had better not start happening now, because I'm still fully dependent on those things.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that is the actual dukkha that people don't want to experience.
[SPEAKER_04]: The irony is that how to not experience that anxiety, most of the time, is by building up more acquisitions, in order to distract yourself from it, which actually then aggravates the problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you get caught up in this circle,
[SPEAKER_04]: Which is a vicious one.
[SPEAKER_04]: And as long as that's not understood, your whole situation basically deteriorates.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which is exactly opposite of the reality development.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's one good point.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you have to recognize that you can't get around the fact that suffering depends on acquisition.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: As they say.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's something that people have to hammer in, especially these days, because
[SPEAKER_02]: There's the idea that, you know, you can have your cake and eat it too.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you just find the perfect method, you can have your acquisitions and, you know, dance away from the suffering at the same time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maneuver around it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the thing is, suffering is, like, you can find a... you can find a good
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a technique to outrun it, but the thing is, you are creating it in the first place, out of those acquisitions, and all of those things will eventually have to fail at some point.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter how much it works right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And those acquisitions will be factually
[SPEAKER_02]: Increasing, at the very least, at the time of death or when things really start going wrong, that will increase the intensity of how much that's going to hit you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, when, you know, you're against the wall, you don't have anywhere to run, then you're going to see, oh, actually,
[SPEAKER_02]: The only way to truly not end up this way, was to not build up these things in the first place.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then it's going to be too late.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, then it's too late.
[SPEAKER_04]: And also, we should perhaps...
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm not sure if this is where we want to go with the discussion now, but acquisitions, people might think, well, that is just material things like a car, a house, or a family.
[SPEAKER_04]: But actually, in the context of... that's not wrong, as such.
[SPEAKER_04]: You have to start with that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, you have to start on that level.
[SPEAKER_04]: But actually, acquisitions is regarding the five aggregates as mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but see... That's the fundamental level of giving up acquisitions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but see, the point is, like, when you emphasize that level too much, people will think, okay, no, no, but then the...
[SPEAKER_02]: I can still keep the...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: The house and the...
[SPEAKER_02]: I just have to give it the five arrogants.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, in a sense, yeah, so we should start by recognizing that that there is also mundane acquisitions and you want to create some basic order in your life there, which means basically less is more.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, it's a popular phrase, but it's not wrong in this context.
[SPEAKER_04]: And from there, you you create the space and the mental energy as well to find the actual, let's say,
[SPEAKER_04]: A fundamental level where the reflection of dhamma takes place.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, the thing is, like, without giving up those things...
[SPEAKER_02]: Giving up those things in and of themselves doesn't mean you have understood acquisition.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But there's no way that you will understand what acquisition is without giving up those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to, like, dig through the...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like soil, kind of, on top of, like...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you talk about the five aggregates being the base, like, you still have to, kind of, dig down to it by, you know, giving up...
[SPEAKER_01]: The kind of more mundane things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the five aggregates, whatever you might think the five aggregates are, while you're still engaging with the secondary results of the five aggregates, which is sense objects, you, like, it's, well, I mean, people see the five aggregates as sense objects.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's, like, the most
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a perverse, egregious thing, but it does happen that way, because they didn't cultivate that prerequisite of actually... Like, your understanding of the five aggregates, even if you have no theoretical information about the dhamma and these mystical insights of, you know, things constantly changing or something, your understanding of the five aggregates is more accurate
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're restrained, then if you're not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, if you're not restrained, and then watching all these mystical revelations in your meditation, actually... Yeah, and those mystical revelations have nothing to do with it anyway, just to be clear.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it can be quite distracting, because it's the novelty of it and all that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But all you have to fundamentally ask yourself is
[SPEAKER_02]: Am I sure that when sickness, aging and death come, that this is actually freeing me from that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or is it just providing me some form of entertainment that's taking me away from that?
[SPEAKER_02]: So...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or is it just giving me a way to pretend that sickness, aging and death don't exist, because it's just these particles constantly changing or something, and therefore I don't suffer, which is going back to that discussion we had about not denying the significance of things.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, all of that, like, if you haven't been able to develop these precepts and prerequisites, all the insights you might be developing about anicca, dukkha, anatta, all these things, they will come through that container of wrong view, of denying the
[SPEAKER_02]: the fact that things are real, denying the fact that there is choice, that's why you would end up with these ideas that, oh, my, you know, it's it's just determinism, because, because pācītyasana-upāda, you know, it's one moment conditioning the next, and therefore I have no choice, because everything is just this constant process.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you end up just denying things, again, to find a shortcut to free yourself from that suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: All this is just a dream, an illusion.
[SPEAKER_04]: If my ignorance is dispelled, I will discover what is really, really real, which is some sort of ultimate nothingness behind the scene.
[SPEAKER_02]: Where sickness, aging and death can't go, supposedly.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, yeah, if that's somebody's background view, which is actually what mysticism is, this distinction between appearance, then, inadvertently, somebody will be cultivating ill-will.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because things are there, but if you assume that they shouldn't be there,
[SPEAKER_04]: Because you think they're only there on account of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_04]: And when the ignorance is dispelled, you will see what things really are.
[SPEAKER_04]: Namely, nothing.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, you sit there and you realize, well, things are still there.
[SPEAKER_04]: I must be doing it wrong.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you just keep working yourself up, factually cultivating ill will, rather than actually recognizing that things being there was never the problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, I mean, the thing is, it might generally work.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, it might get to advanced stages or whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the thing is, all of it remains within the container of
[SPEAKER_02]: Didn't you actually address sickness, aging, and death?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or did you just kind of took a like a detour to somewhere else?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so then, fundamentally, you did not.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's it's the...
[SPEAKER_02]: Fundamentally, the resistance to suffering is a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not that you don't see the
[SPEAKER_00]: But it could be... yeah, so... you could say the resistance isn't the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: The resistance of resistance is the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's why you start from the position of resistance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you start from the position of resistance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's seeing that and not seeing that as problematic.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, seeing that the thing, the fact that things are unpleasant, is in and of itself not the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why... And the Buddha had unpleasant experiences.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he didn't have a choice of aversion towards them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the... that's the... the distinction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you recognize weights.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, I'm suffering a kind of unpleasant feeling, but that's not... that's not the fault of the unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the fault of my lack of understanding in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you just keep that perspective, and then...
[SPEAKER_02]: At least you won't be able to go too far into thinking that unpleasant feeling is a problem in and of itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, and it doesn't matter where it comes from.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter if it's bodily pain of, you know, in your heat, cold elements and stuff, or if it's mental displeasure of
[SPEAKER_02]: The confinement that results from restraining your bodily behavior, your verbal behavior, and your mental behavior, all the displeasure that comes from that, none of it, in and of itself, is a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why the second Noble Truth is craving is the root of suffering, not suffering is the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it doesn't matter what feeling it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it says any feeling, whether it's past, present or future, high or low, inferior or superior, it doesn't matter where it came from.
[SPEAKER_02]: All of it has to be understood in the same way.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how, as you said before, you go through it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't explain it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't hide from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just
[SPEAKER_02]: Abandon your wrong attitude in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And while the thing remains the same, you free yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you don't need to manage anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, the most intense displeasure...
[SPEAKER_02]: Displeasure like a mountain.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not that the mountain of sickness, aging, and death changed.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you turn it into something else.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why it doesn't suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, it's still the same mountain.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't affect you anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a big difference.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I thought we could also mention what is it that reveals that suffering that you need to learn to not try to get rid of immediately.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not that having not changed your
[SPEAKER_02]: There has to be some practical giving up that actually exposes that discrepancy between the place where your mind is, the expectations that it has,
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there has to be some factual renunciation for you to start to see that suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not just like, I keep living the same way and I just reflect on these truths.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because any philosopher can do that, really.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not a... What makes it actually a practice that's developing your mind is when you practically
[SPEAKER_02]: Live according to the recognition that, at least taking it on faith, that certain things that you do are making the suffering worse.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, restraining yourself, first in regard to the body, in regard to the speech, in regard to your mind, but most importantly, those first two, as a starting point,
[SPEAKER_02]: Naturally, the suffering will... you don't even need to look for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if you're not reflecting on it, if you have been living like 99% of people today, that suffering will start to reveal itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: The suffering, again, that you're not looking for, it's going to be visible and evident just on account of you not doing something.
[SPEAKER_02]: And actually, that's already a red flag.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, telling you, revealing to you that this, that there's a problem here.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I need to keep doing these things, which fundamentally I might not be able to do, if my environment changes, if my access to these things changes, that's already a red flag that there's a dependence there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's fundamentally, that is what the suffering is.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's that liability
[SPEAKER_02]: to displeasure when you don't get things the way you want.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like I'm free from suffering just in the present because I happen to have the right circumstances.
[SPEAKER_02]: The suffering is there even if everything goes well because
[SPEAKER_02]: It could not go well.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, that is the... that's also the definition in quite a few discourses of what is the origin of suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: Having to put up with things that you do not want and not getting the things that you want.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then it says, in short, the five holding aggregates are what is suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then it dives all the way to the to the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you are practically saying that if people are hearing this and they say, well, everything is going okay, but that is monks talking about suffering and so on, well, start keeping the eight precepts, not just for a weekend or for a month, but have the view that, you know, I'm going to keep this up.
[SPEAKER_04]: For the rest of my life, because that's how you're going to feel the weight of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, you can see how there is this sort of habitual momentum, which might not be immediately apparent, but stick to it and it will be there.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then there is the choice.
[SPEAKER_04]: Am I now going to keep those precepts?
[SPEAKER_04]: Which means I have to resist some tendency that I never saw before, because I was always running with it.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is how dukkha for most people will practically begin to show its face, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a good point.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you can't just take it on for...
[SPEAKER_02]: If you want to really start recognizing that suffering, so that you can understand it, you can't just take it up temporarily, because it's like, well, any drug addict can give up his drug for a weekend, and he knows he's gonna have it in the end.
[SPEAKER_02]: If he has it good enough,
[SPEAKER_02]: Alternative sensual motivation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you know, he has to go to a job interview or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: He can give up his drug, no problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you will only really start feeling it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even, I mean, literally, in the case of a drug addict, when he tells himself, no, I'm never going to have this again.
[SPEAKER_02]: But anybody can do that for like two weeks, one month, two months.
[SPEAKER_04]: That doesn't mean much.
[SPEAKER_04]: And also, if one wants to start thinking about death rightly,
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, this is how you start.
[SPEAKER_04]: By giving things up, in the sense, I am never going to do this again.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that weight is experientially what death will be for you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not your ideas like, well, when I'm dead, I'm not there.
[SPEAKER_04]: Therefore, death is no longer a problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: And all this kind of abstract rationalizations, which quite miss the mark, start to create some basic order in your life, i.e.
[SPEAKER_04]: aligned with the eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, there will be experientially a foundation for you,
[SPEAKER_04]: To sort of get the feeling, but in a non-sentimental sense, of what death actually is.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will get in contact with your feelings, literally, by keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not by, you know, doing some sort of a new age practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will start to see your feelings on the right level just by doing that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you actually mentioned it, like, that formulation of the first noble truth that ends with the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's saying that the fundamental suffering is the five aggregates, and it gives that as a kind of summary of the things that preceded.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's precisely by exposing yourself to these things that you necessarily wanted to see in the beginning, like the fact that you're liable to contact with things that you don't want to be in contact with, liable to not be in contact with things that you do want to be in contact with.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the first level, too.
[SPEAKER_04]: The origin is the craving.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, by
[SPEAKER_02]: Ironically, that's the route through which you will get to see the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not by, like, keeping staying in your comfortable environment and then thinking, what are the five aggregates?
[SPEAKER_04]: So... And then writing a PhD about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why, then, even that, like, you won't be able to...
[SPEAKER_02]: Practically, reflect on what death is, unless you have taken on some amount of that self-discipline, in terms of the precepts, in terms of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, like renunciation, you could say it's a form of losing things before they are taken away from you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you lose things, so as to practice
[SPEAKER_02]: And to develop your mind in regard to loss before it even comes.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the principle of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't wait until it gets ripped away from you and it was like already so encrusted and embedded into your hand that it rips your whole hand off with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You actually take it off while it's still only a little bit sticky.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you develop yourself, so that you can... you never take it off.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, that's the assembly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like a hot iron ball, and it falls in your hand, and you just drop it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because you actually... but you... but you need to experience it.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's hot and it's burning.
[SPEAKER_02]: And see, the whole problem is all these actions, and all these, you know, unrestrained behavior, and then the whole
[SPEAKER_02]: Psychologization and techniques and management methods that come on top of it are all directed at not feeling the heat of that ball while you're holding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.